hello and welcome this is active
inference guest stream
65.1 it's December 6th
2023 we'll be hearing from Phoebe clet
and Dan Simpson on basian world models
for explainable transparent reasoning
there will be a presentation followed by
a discussion so thank you for joining
Phoebe very much looking forward to the
presentation to
you awesome thanks for having us uh yeah
and I'm really excited to chat with you
all about how we might start to
integrate today's state-of-the-art
language models um into more
probabilistic machinery and what that
might buy
us all right let's get right into it um
all right so some of the things that I'm
hoping to discuss today uh include why
we might use a language model for
something that isn't long form text
generation uh and how we might do that
uh and then motivate a little bit kind
of why we might need a world model um
what simple uh self-organizing World
models might look like uh and even in
the simplest cases how we might start to
use those um as effective recommendation
engines in the wild today uh and then a
little bit of discussion about kind of
where this research is
going all
right so what are language models good
at uh today's uh especially large
language models um are trained on next
token production uh so this means given
a sequence of tokens uh we're going to
estimate um which token is most likely
to come next uh maybe rephrasing that a
little bit um we might also say that
language models uh are trained to
estimate uh which sequences of tokens or
words are likely uh the caveat being
likely to appear in the training set um
but today our training sets are are
quite
extensive so given this simple training
objective it's um our arguably
surprising uh that we've seen language
models do as well as they have uh in in
really impressive tasks uh so they start
to demonstrate like really great um
language understanding meaning like the
semantics of language itself uh not just
the the syntax of kind of like which
sentences make sense um they've also
started to demonstrate some uh World
Knowledge so implicitly learning kind of
how the world works just through our own
human abstraction um and how we uh
articulate that uh we start to see
language models falter at tasks um which
look more like symbolic problem solving
uh so math in particular we see this in
programming although we're getting
better at this uh and in general any
kind of like long-term planning tasks
which require abstract reasoning um so
we see this also in problems that look
like this which are word problems um but
which are really about kind of like
understanding abstractly how these kind
of abstract objects relate to each other
uh and again this shouldn't be
surprising that language models struggle
to do to do things like this um since
it's so far off from their original
training objective um and in particular
even when we arrive at the right answer
in some of these cases it's really hard
to know after the fact kind of the
reasoning for how we ended up at the
right answer in this particular case uh
and maybe more fundamentally uh if we
don't know where the abstraction is
happening or where the reasoning is
happening it's very hard to guide that
process uh and so this starts to
motivate the need for something that
looks more like an explicit World model
uh and now to start to borrow some uh
words from Yasha Benjo this is one of
the um kind of biggest issues with
today's language models is arguably that
we're asking the language model to be
both the inference machine and the world
model implicitly uh when this uh doesn't
quite make sense um and so some things
that we might hope for in a world model
uh are to model causal relationships to
be really adapt at modeling using
uncertainty uh and to be a modular um
Yan Lun puts this in a in a similar way
so uh we might kind of ask a world model
uh to be able to distinguish between
which details are important versus
irrelevant uh and to be able to make
predictions uh that can be performed in
sort of like this abstract space of
representations um and so hopefully in
the next uh following slides we're going
to motivate um what it might look like
to use language models as the inference
machines in maybe like the simplest case
of self-organizing world models um and
even in those most simple cases how we
start to get uh something much closer to
the kind of uh explainable reasoning um
which I think lots of us are grasping
for right
now all right so in a very simple case
we might think of a world model as
simply a collection of hypotheses where
we model confidence um over over each of
those
hypotheses uh and in particular we care
about predictive World models so given
some evidence or data that we've
observed in the world we'd like to
propose uh the the world models um which
best explain uh the evidence that we've
observed uh and if that language s
sounded leading uh it was indeed we are
proposing in this case to use a Bas rule
which we all know and love um which
tells us exactly how to update our
beliefs given some new evidence uh and
so uh when our hypotheses uh are kind of
these uh brely random variables this
bottom term uh can simply be expanded um
into this this equation on the slide and
so the the real tricky part in this
computation uh is the likelihood piece
um so given this evidence given that uh
our hypothesis is true what's the
likelihood that we would have observed
the evidence uh and the the claim that
we're making is that language models are
actually this is this is like a natural
task task of a language model um when
our evidence and our hypothesis are both
semantic objects as we discussed
language models are kind of trained
exactly to understand which sequences of
text are likely um so asking it to
prompting it in a clever way such that
we can extract uh this particular
likelihood is actually really natural
so how do we do this um so we come up
with this kind of clever prompting
scheme um that allows us to extract
again exactly How likely uh is is this
to have C so given that our hypothesis
is H in this setting uh and our evidence
is this uh cly e um we only need to
change our evidence into the conditional
form and then phrase the question like
this to the to the language model so the
input sequence of text uh goes is like
given that you know potentially if our
hypothesis is like Walmart has been sely
impacted by covid-19 pandemic would we
have observed the evidence um that
Walmart laid off 10% of the material
staff um and so either using something
like f shot prompting or guidance or
some kind of control generation
technique um we can ensure that our
language model outputs either yes or no
and then uh use the logits from its
answer uh to at that
probability um and again the the claim
here is that like this is actually
really natural task um to ask of a
language model um that leverages uh its
like innate reasoning engine uh better
than just kind of allowing it to ramble
uh using using text
sometimes and we can even make this
updating scheme um a bit more
sophisticated using things like
Precision waiting um so this will buy
our our posterior over hypothesis um
either towards our prior or our evidence
that we've observed um based on how
confident we are in our prior and in our
evidence all
right so the world models that we've
seen so far um are fairly simple uh in
particular we're modeling all our
hypotheses as independent from each
other uh and this seems like a a large
simplifying assumption um so how might
we support more complex World models
where we condition our hypotheses on
each
other all right so another thing that um
hopefully will be familiar to this crowd
basinets have been around for forever
and um are often used to model
mechanistic failures and en llarge
systems um and can be understood simply
as distribution or each variable depends
on some small number of ancestor
variables uh perhaps more intuitively we
you can also think these think of these
as directed graphs um where we have
edges between variables um which are
directed in the sense that the parent is
conditioned on the
child so let's see an
example all right so now we have uh two
different kinds of
hypotheses uh the ones which are kind of
parents in our simple setup um are kind
of qualitatively more abstract than the
children um so our two children nudes um
are similar to the hypothesis we saw
before um Market sentiment for Best Buy
poor or Walmart will grow its physical
footprint this year uh and then the more
abstract hypothesis being retailers were
negatively infected by
covid-19 um and so then we specify uh
this conditional structure um either
kind of in a classical sense by
specifying all of the joint
probabilities up front um or
alternatively learning it given some
healthy amount of train data uh and
again we're proposing that instead of
doing that uh intensive process we can
use language models to extract those
probabilities in a natural
way um and so one natural complaint at
this point might be like well this space
is going to start to get very large um
if we're trying to update these beliefs
in real time given some large data
stream this is going to become
intractable uh given our current
framework um so how might we start to
augment
that luckily there's been a lot of work
historically done on this problem uh and
we can start to use things like message
passing to update our beliefs in an
approximate way um so as long as our
baset has a tree dependency structure we
can use things like the Su product uh
algorithm to update our beliefs and I
don't want you to worry too much about
the equations on this slide if you've
seen this before uh this kind of
recursive structure will look familiar
but if not the general kind of intuitive
idea that we're going to compute these
messages from all of the children or the
neighboring nodes and use those to
propagate through the graph to update um
each independent
belief but let's just see an
example all right so suppose we observe
some new evidence and we'd like to know
how should we update the probability um
over hypothesis a which as you remember
is the parent node in our graph um all
right so B here on the left hand side is
the belief um XA is essentially like
just the very able representing the
hypothesis a um and then the Fe and the
side terms are specified um by our
language model or the um the Bas net in
the classical sense uh and so we're
summing over all of the variables all of
the values that the variables XB and XC
can take which in our case of course is
just zero and one um so if you uh you
might recognize at this point that this
is indeed the exact marginal probability
um for the hypothesis a um and that's
because our graph is Simply Connected in
this example so in general this isn't
true but um turns out to be the case in
in our
example and again uh we can compute
these Fe and S terms uh using the
language model
itself all right so because we're all
levers of free energy here going to walk
through kind of how this is uh maybe the
first example of uh a self- evidencing
um or minimizing free energy um kind of
model so um as we noted belief
propagation isn't exact for more
complicated graphs and so uh it makes
sense and might be useful to ask the
question um you know how far apart or
when are our beliefs um close to the
exact marginals uh and so we often use
um things like K Divergence to compare
the difference between two probability
distributions and that um is explicated
uh on the right hand side uh and then
those of us um
who who are uh like have a background in
physics might recognize boltzman's law
as well um so this is just the idea that
we might represent the probability of a
given State using an energy function uh
and we're not going to accept this as
truth maybe as some of us have done in
the past um but we are going to just use
it as a definition for this energy
function such that when we plug in that
term here um and expand out we start to
see these first two terms like a lot
like the kind of energy and entropy
functions which we are used to and
indeed we can just uh classify those two
terms uh as the Gibs free energy
function um yeah which makes me happy to
to see this all coming together uh and
in particular it might make sense uh
just to note at this point that using um
world models which are self-organizing
in this sense uh seems to be very
compelling since the kind of world model
which we want is one um which promotes
the evidence that we've seen so far
um why is it uh useful to to formulate
this in terms of free energy besides the
fact that we all um find it compelling
here uh well you can make a lot of
progress by constructing analytically
tractable approximations of Gibs free
energy often um I'm not going to go into
the details here uh but here are two
examples where for that been
fruitful all right great um so now I'm
going to chat briefly about kind of how
we might use recommendation systems like
or how we might use these systems as
recommendation systems uh and indeed in
the world uh
today all right so one like prime
example for aware system like this might
be useful is is a situation where we
have kind of lots of data incoming uh at
very high frequencies and we always want
to have some set of like naturally
discrete hypotheses that we're modeling
beliefs over um which are being kept up
to dat um at a at a very regular Cadence
uh and so actually a lot of the the
muscle here is just reformatting
documents or however our data comes in
as evidences this is not always obvious
or easy to do um but once you've kind of
figured out that part uh and in
particular um we've been using things
like rag retrieval augmented generation
or um embedding based systems to kind of
figure out when data that's in in is
relevant to a given hypothesis um once
you've kind of built up that Machinery
the actual updating computations as
we've shown um already is actually
pretty simple so we do these likelihood
computations and we update our beliefs
uh and then at any given time we can
query that model um for our marginal
distribution um over any given
hypothesis uh and it turns out that this
um kind of setup has many practical
applications
it's also noteworthy that even with very
simple systems like these um these are
like out of the box controllable and
explainable um so just by storing the
magnitude and the direction of the
update to the posterior for each piece
of evidence that we observe we have a
very natural built-in explanation for
our belief at any given time uh and that
makes kind of like these applications
where folks might really like to use a
language model but really require like a
robust like causal relationship between
the outputs and the explanation um which
you don't get from a language model on
its own a system like this can be very
appealing in those
situations all right so now on to
further
work so everything that we've discussed
today um is early work towards um
integrating language models uh into more
probabilistic Frameworks uh and there's
been a lot of exciting work done uh in
this vein right now um some important
questions which are especially
interesting to me or which parts of the
world model should be learned versus
encoded um and how do we want
intelligence to scale so I mean that uh
both in the sense of composing systems
naturally there should be some very like
natural way that we can compose to
intelligent systems and also such that
we can scale them with compute uh and I
don't mean to restrict myself either to
the kinds of compute that we have today
we're also working at some uh exciting
new Computing paradigms at normal um
which might be more compatible with
software uh of this
nature um also the two folks that we
referenced at the beginning of the talk
Jeff Hinton and Yan Lun have done really
exciting work in this area um which is
yeah very inspiring and so in particular
G Nets are also probabilistic graphical
models um which I think folks will find
um a natural next step in Reading uh
yeah if if you so
desire and that's um that's it for
me awesome thank you wow
very
cool Dan do you want to give a first
reflection or thought and then meanwhile
anyone who's watching live please feel
free to write questions I'll relay them
in um absolutely um so hi I'm I'm I'm
Dan I work with Phoebe on this project
um and yes the um I think the thing
that's most exciting about this for me
personally is sort of twofold one of
them is that it's a way of
avoiding sort of having to trust a
language model to understand and reason
about text um
because they're
not it's not that they're bad the thing
is the the extremely strange thing about
language models is they're quite good at
being almost good enough um but they're
never quite what you could use you could
never use a language model to I don't
know uh
sort of triage like an important sort of
situation where a bunch of different
things are coming in you have to make a
decision about which is important the
reason you can't do that is you you
simply cannot understand the encoded
biases you cannot get it to reliably
generate reasoning you can ask it for
reasoning but the thing that it prints
out is not the reasoning that it used
internally because it doesn't
reason um fundamentally while these have
input and output that are natural
language they are not artificially
intelligent they are just prediction
machines um and so we have to be very
careful about not anthropomorphizing
them so this is a way of using those
incredibly powerful prediction machines
in a framework where we can um make sure
that
we uh essentially keep a record of what
we're doing so the human can look at it
because I mean there's a lot of talk in
this world about sort of posthuman AI
and those sorts of things the idea that
the machines will become intelligent
enough or the machines will rise up in a
slightly more alarming Type of Way um
and that's all great and wonderful but
that's not particularly interesting to
us at normal we're much more interested
in sort of having you know mimicking
explicit decision processes so that a
human can audit them and can make these
things work so that's kind of the like
the area that we're we're sort of coming
from awesome all right I'll go to a
question from the chat so Josh asks
great talk where does hypothesis
relevance enter the calculus is it
folded into confidence not sure if it
ought to be just saw hypothesis
relevance
mentioned hypothesis relevance does that
mean um
like which hypotheses are conditioned on
each other is it possible to ask a
clarifying question there maybe Dan you
have a they they can follow up but yeah
like um I also wondered about this like
you might know what was relevant maybe
the temperature and the rainfall were
relevant but then how does this approach
help us understand when one of those
relevant factors no longer is relevant
or when a new relevant Factor comes into
play yeah these are great questions um
so I think in terms of understanding in
an automatic sense when two hypotheses
are are relevant to each other we can
leverage um embedding type you know
language models for this kind of thing
also um if we don't have a more kind of
like structured human intuitive sense
for when to hypotheses are are related
uh in terms of like how those
relationships evolve over time this is
something that's really interesting to
me and I think looking at the the theory
behind structure learning or when we
propose to add new nodes to the network
or propos to add a new Edge to the
network or things like this uh is a
really exciting research Direction um
although I I don't have like a silver
bullet answer to to how we should do
that um just to like add a little bit
more to that um it is like it is a
really interesting research Direction um
like one of one of the things that
Phoebe mentioned in the talk is that
there is a difficult step that we're not
talking about which is actually
translating this natural language into
reasonable hypotheses so there is a step
in there where you take essentially a
chunk of text and you have to
decide if this is a hypothesis if this
is a hypothesis we've seen before if
this is a sub hypothesis or a
clarification of a hypothesis that we've
seen before and so on and so forth so
that's in some sense part of the data
processing and it's it is an important
step and one that we are sort of
continuing to work on and refine uh the
other thing like a different sort of
interpretation of the question around
relevance is um around sort of is the
hypothesis relevant to the thing that
you're looking at I mean we could have a
hypothesis that the sky is blue but if
we are deciding to deciding you know
whether whether or not we need to check
that car's oil like the the the truth or
not of the color of the sky is very
irrelevant and that then comes into the
nice thing about having your world
described as a um collection of
statements with truth values associated
with them in that you can directly
reason over them so you can put a
classical decision
framework um over that to take into
account both the sort of the knowledge
you have of the world and also like
which parts of these worlds are are sort
of unknown so in that sort of situation
the person using the world model to
Constructor um a a sort of decision or
an output will
be responsible in some sense for
assigning a weight or a cost to each
hypothesis being true and for some of
those hypotheses obviously it will be
zero um because again we do not care
about the color of the sky if all I want
to know if is if I need to change the
oil in my car um so that's the that's
the sort of the other end of the answer
so there's a version of the answer at
the start of the information flow and
there's a version of the answer at the
end of the information flow but it is a
tricky uh point and one that we are sort
of continuing to iterate on to try and
find
sort of good wayes on both ends of
that yeah well a lot there um it's very
interesting how in that presentation in
response I heard both about probability
distributions on rules and rules on
probability
distributions and like with which one
whether it's the tail wagging the dog or
the horse in the cart how to design
these synthetic intelligence systems
that appropriately bring
together aspects that are more symbolic
more rule like and then more
probabilistic more embedding like so
where does that land with you or how do
you see the design of these systems with
mixed symbolic and probabilistic
components yeah yeah that's a great
point and I think this really gets it
like which parts of the world model
should be learned um or should be
represented in some like more discret
space versus like encoded based on our
own human intuition for rules and
structure um and I think like maybe this
is would be fairly represented as a
copout answer but I think it depends a
lot on the application uh I think like
when we're developing systems like this
and and just trying to iterate through
as many different um hypotheses uh as
you can quickly um like choosing an
application and and benchmarking and
testing and seeing like what actually
works um is is a go-to strategy for us
uh in terms of like well which parts are
should be fixed and are actually helpful
um in to increase reliability such that
like we can use our human intuition for
how this particular you know system is
built uh versus like well this is
something that we we want uncertainty
over that's like a really important part
of the learning process for us in terms
of um yeah that kind of iteration um so
I think I think it probably depends on
the
application yeah it's um it it
definitely depends on the application
it's
also um like depends on where the actual
challenge points are so we've got like
outside of this we've got sort of a few
other things that we've released
publicly that kind of look at this idea
of there
being like external rules to the uh um
to the the system and whether or not we
can add those in so one of them is
something called constrained generation
where we we sort of force the model to
only produce something valid and that's
sort of quite a useful way of removing
one particular aspect of stress to from
the model which is that it may make sort
of
syntactically or sort of in somehow
incoherent um outputs that don't follow
the rules
and then we can then focus with the rest
of our energy we can then take that as
given and focus with the rest of our
energy on improving the bit that we
don't have rules for um so so those
sorts of things and sort of a different
version is trying to improve something
by saying no you broke a rule we need to
like go back and make this not sort of
true so this kind of um of Chain of
Thought prompting type of idea
um so so yeah the um the symbolic and
the
probabilistic
um I think in our minds live very
closely together as two tools that don't
completely solve the same
problem um and I think there's sort of
in in the world of I'm not sure how
familiar anyone in the audience is with
language modeling but like in the world
of language modeling before this sort of
explosion of neural networks and
artificial int type methods uh there was
a lot of work on symbolics of language
and grammars and all of that sort of
stuff and that work pushed quite a long
way forward um and this work is pushing
quite a long way forward and I suspect
the next thing is going to involve them
joining up again uh because they each
have good points they each have bad
points and you know two wrongs don't
necessarily make her right but they can
make her less
wrong nice yeah recently we heard from
Elliot Murphy and talking about the
neural Linguistics and about how the
statistics of language are not the rules
of language you can always come up with
a new expression that's never been
uttered that's not going to be in the
training distribution or any
distribution MH okay I'll ask a question
in the chat from upcycle Club they wrote
what are some of the key challenges
associated with developing such basian
World
models
hm I think we've touched on a bunch of
them um the ones that are most top of
mind for me right now are are this the
structure learning thing that came up so
how do we understand like when to
propose new hypotheses and how to
integrate those into the models um and
then yeah just figuring out like yeah I
I guess this like proposal and evolution
process of the nodes themselves um since
everything else like the framework like
works pretty automatically and in a
reasonable way uh thank you B thank you
to the development of language models um
but kind of moving from this like more
uh discret case into a continuous case
um which like more fully represents the
space that we're learning over um can be
challenging yeah um I would also say
that like it's a sort of a
saying let's go in that direction uh
there's a c saying in this world that um
that sort of no model ever survives its
first encounter with data um and that
that becomes true here as well so
there's lots of like as we've been
building these things and using them we
found lots of little spiky Edge Corners
with sort of making sure that the
language model is actually doing what we
wanted to do so there are a lot of
questions in building these things
around how do you actually test that the
the the components of it are actually
working the way you want and then on
like a broader level how do you compare
something that is fundamentally trying
to solve a different
problem um to other methods so we are
solving a problem under the constraints
that we want a fully auditable
system um we could also solve all of
these problems by a thing called in
context learning which is basically
putting the context into the prompt of a
large language model and asking it the
answer and that also
works uh especially when you've got
things like GPT 4 which are just wonders
and glories um it works really well so
then we come to the question of how do
we actually make the case for this from
a like a bigger picture perspective can
it be more than just a like can we find
benchmarks that
reflect um the structural advantages of
this approach over something like in
context learning uh that don't come
across as false so that's kind of like a
a a stranger answer because it's not
really about like actually developing
the world model it's about sort of
convincing other people that it's a good
idea um and that's you know that that is
a thing that is true of essentially all
of the things on this slide as well they
are all quite complex and odd little
methods um that you know there's a
there's a degree to which well we
definitely can solve this an easier way
um so what is the thing that what is the
the the application or The Benchmark
where we can say no if you do it the
easier way you will fail at this
measurable thing
very interesting um so you mentioned the
self
evidencing advantages
of using World models that are self-
evidencing rather than reward maximizing
for example so how do you see that
playing out and I can connect it back to
active inference of course but how do
you see this self- evidencing centrality
play out in the kinds of models
described
here yeah I think there are a couple
reasons why it's so compelling to me uh
and the first just has to do with
explainability right like it's really
convincing to people to say like well
why why did we predict this why do we
believe this well the this is the actual
real world data that we've observed such
that you know this this is the impact
that that's had uh and then I think like
uh I don't know you hear a lot about
like designing these really complicated
reward functions which are often very
clever but which um often I feel like
are close to being a pitfall because
they very easily become like
disconnected from like the complex world
that we're trying to model and so you
end up in like weird local maximums or
minimums and um yeah you start like just
kind of uh solving the problem that
you've designed versus like the problem
which actually exists and so um I I just
have always left the idea that what we
should be doing is um kind of self-
evidencing and from an intuitive sense
that feels like what it feels like what
an intelligence system should
do uh
yeah yeah I actually don't have anything
interesting to add to that I just agree
with
fa that explainability and the capacity
to explicitly reference previous data
including like leave one out so
techniques from non-parametric
statistics about the effect of adding in
another piece of data or removing a
piece of data um and then just like to
bring it to like a homeostatic setting
which is a commonly considered an active
inference like we're trying to be within
a homeostatic temperature range of
37 yes we could propose reward functions
but as those start to include
open-endedness and exploration structure
learning just like you described it phbe
like we're solving the problem as
designed rather than the actual question
of the homeostatic temperature and the
sort of path of least action first
principles physics grounded intelligence
perspective from active inference is
like make it the kind of thing that
measures itself at
37 and then as long as it is it is and
when it isn't it's dead and that's the
kind of mortal
Computing crossover which is like
outside of its zone of
surprise it it's not just that it's
getting a bad grade in the class
that is like a deeper failure signal
than that and to understand okay when is
it a yellow flag when is it a red flag
in terms of the new scientific
literature coming in those have
plain straightforward ways to interpret
that developing larger higher order
apparatuses will never turn to that kind
of Basil
Simplicity yeah couldn't agree
more yeah AB I mean absolutely it also
like the other thing that it can do
quite well is deal
with
essentially outlier studies so SI
situations where you have a new piece of
information that is strongly conflict
with all the previous pieces of
information um and trying to sort of
work through what that really
means um and there's a like there's a
degree to
which uh we can even sort of extend this
process uh to multiple agents that have
these belief systems and then look at
sort of consensuses of experts or
weighted cons consensus of experts so
for instance you could have like a we
vein type of situation where somebody
really over indexes to every new piece
of
information um and you would do that
with you know technically you do that
with maybe a power posterior type thing
or you can have somebody who's built in
strong priors in a particular direction
um and you can then like take your
consensus of
artificial um sort of decision making
all of which has within their Universe
well reasoned updates to the data and
then you can look and try and work out
what that swarm of experts can tell you
um and sort of do very empirical things
like try and you know work out which of
these experts is doing well at a
particular moment in time um because you
know there could be there could be times
when the world's very or the problem
that you're solving is very chaotic in
which case the over indexing uh expert
would probably be a pretty pretty solid
bet um while there are other times where
sort of things are pretty stable and you
probably it would be possible that the
um sort of the more conservative expert
is more uh sort of empirically making
good decisions and good recommendations
so there's like a lot of ways that we
can not just like incorporate these sort
of
homeostasis type ideas but we can also
change what that means for different
agents and artifici like do that
artificially and then combine them
together to try and get
a almost like a
um uh
like blanking on the word but you know
um a forecast under a sort of a
hypothetical set of situations and we
can actually sort of bring those ideas
of the world forward and see what
happens when they sort of meet with
actual
information yeah this angle of mixture
of experts as it's sometimes called more
in the language model space or
ecosystems of shared intelligence or
diverse intelligences in the active
inference area like that's very
interesting obviously has connections
Back To Human teams and teams of Beyond
humans and so on um a lot of this is
still text based so maybe you did or
didn't mention what representation the
base graphs are but
they're plain text like and there was a
lot of discussion about bringing from
natural language scientific papers or
however it is into a structured form and
then the explain method that you showed
kind of take
the structured form and just giving a
little syntactic fluency so it looks
human readable so how do you see that
Essence coming into play with multimodal
models and then with action in the world
that isn't just developing the next text
token but uh robotic actuator or
modifying some other control element of
the world
yeah that's a really good question um I
honestly haven't thought much about
multimodal stuff in this particular
context but I think um I think the
framework is is General enough at this
point such that it it's definitely could
support lots of different
modalities um I I'm yeah I'd be really
curious to see how this did with
something like audio in particular uh
yeah and then um to your point about
like uh yeah this maybe like Reet versus
continuous um relationship I think I
think that's like part of what we're
we're learning is how to go from like
these long natural text documents to a
system which is appropriately
discretizing um our hypotheses um such
that we we have these like meaningful
explanations like you mentioned um so I
think yeah I think
like continuing to develop like uh
robust ways of um surfacing those
explanations is a big part of this as
well um like over time we're going to
observe lots and lots and lots of
evidence um how do we make sure like
hypotheses don't get stale and how do we
use evidence to know when they are and
and things like this um are part of that
also I don't know if that directly
answered your question but that's some
of the stuff that I've been thinking
about related to
that so in
the I I
mean in examples like sort of moving
towards otics and sort of tech video
generation and image generation other
audio other sort of multimodalities
um to be honest I think of these
processes in general as enabling a like
building a world model to enable a sort
of sequential decision
process um so if that decision process
happens to be should the robot turn left
and that's what the sort of the decision
proc processes it's it's multimodal in
like a very classical sense that you can
put any type of decision framework over
the top but it's not sort of
generatively multimodal I'm not saying
write me a song that sounds like Beyonce
and a song that sounds like Beyonce
comes out I think this this sort of this
sort of basian world model layer is
blocking towards that sort of thing but
that's that's really not sort of the aim
of what we're trying to do it's
also like within normal like
our almost I I don't want I don't want
to say Mantra or Manifesto because that
sounds culty and no one wants to sound
culty but like our our basic aim is to
always Center like humans within our
process um and
so some of this multimodal stuff it's
less
clear where the human lives so for
instance like a video generation type
thing where does the human live so
keeping it at this abstraction of
sequential decision making then it's a
decision that a that a human could do
you know human with their thumbs could
be moving like a robot around and doing
that sort of stuff um but yeah it's it's
really all about sort of controllability
and auditability for us in sort of a
sequential decision process
so to the extent that that sort of leads
in its multimodal world that that's um
that that's sort of part of what we're
doing and like to some some versions of
multimodality um is we're we're just not
swimming in that particular space um
yeah not a great answer but a long
one let them distill it down
later um in the um
auditability area it almost falls out to
me to be like a synta taxs of
auditability and a semantics at the
syntactic level just tagging or
versioning when a file comes in or when
a given computation is executed that is
basically transfer across all settings
and then where I see you honing in on
with with this work is kind of the
semantic
auditability which is actually how we
compose our accounts I would have driven
but I decided to walk because this
happen and so bringing that different
kind of Trace to to systems is going to
make it
um what will it open up in science or
education or how do you see
this sitting at a consle somebody is at
now and making this different like over
what
timeline
yeah I mean it's really quite nice for
storytelling because as you said you can
say things precisely like
well you know because we observed this
thing or because if we had observed
something else you know like maybe you
can even make statements which are um
yeah conditional in that sense uh I I
think it does like Empower whoever is
sitting in front of this data to feel
like really sure about again like the
the reasoning and that like that went on
uh which to me is is pretty different
from what it feels like to sit in front
of chat gbt even though it's quite
useful often um you know you you try the
code and it works or it doesn't work or
you like you know ask your friend is
this really true um and that feels
pretty different to me from being able
to to look at the evidences themselves
and say like oh well actually if this is
the reason you think that I know that
that evidence is is not true or you know
like you can bring your own human
intuition or World model uh in terms of
validating or um yeah superimposing what
you believe on top of what this system
believes and so that makes it really
easy to make decisions um
quickly I think there's also sort of a
Converse of this which is that it also
makes it clear which evidence was not
used to make a
decision uh and that can be quite
telling in these situations where you
could be worried that a particular type
of evidence isn't being weighted
correctly or isn't being um sort of
formatted correctly so again like if
this is a sort of a a like a system that
builds an
assistant um that sort of does surfaces
all this information and sort of makes a
recommendation with reasoning for a
person that person can then look and be
like and they know what the data is they
can look at the D and say you know why
didn't you consider the make of the car
or why didn't you consider this or why
didn't you consider that and they can
then
use their understanding of what's not
being prominently used by the model to
sort of sense test like it's it's sort
of I mean in some sense that usage of it
is a reformulation of what Phoebe just
said where you use your internal World
model but it's like I think it's it's
important
to know when evidence is being used and
this is like a thing you simply cannot
get um from from like a GPT type thing
or any sort of like prompting type
method we know for instance that like um
the order of the order that you submit
your evidence in is probably going to
matter for a prompting based method okay
that's obviously not true for a basian
update where we have this sort of this
this coherence principle where if you
shuffle your data and enter it in a
different way you will get the same
posterior up to computational artifacts
um so so so all of that is like in my
mind is just as important to
orderability as the ability to write a
report that says I made this decision
for these
reasons yeah well that makes me think
about this kind of view from the inside
interpretability where the rules help
and also knowing what evidence is not
used is importance for compliance and
knowing what information like in a
healthcare setting was or wasn't used um
what about
thermodynamics we heard about free
energy boltzman came
up how do you see the info
Thermo
Nexus what have we learned from the last
100 years of thermodynamic dyamics and
information Theory and all of this and
on the software or
Hardware side how is that kind of a free
energy Nexus
being
used yeah I mean I I'm really excited
about how all of this seems to be coming
together um I think free energy just
keeps showing up in all of these
exciting areas to me we have like a book
club for singular learning Theory and
like they talk all about free energy too
and I think some of those ideas are
really exciting um I mean at normal I
think like the thing that I would
highlight is like this idea of software
Hardware codesign um which is really
special uh and so we're trying to do
this hard and fun dance towards each
other where we're like thinking about
these new kinds of systems and how they
might support each other and um Empower
each other and and yeah how to build
full stack systems um which is really
challenging and and also really exciting
um yeah and I think like from like a
first principles thermodynamics
perspective like like we're all just uh
yeah we're all kind of like mathematics
and physics people at heart so like
going taking like uh you know all of
what people have learned in language
modeling and all of that like um very
much to heart as well like I think
approaching whatever problem that we're
facing from a first principles how do
physical systems work in the world what
do we really what are the assumptions
we're really comfortable with uh and
building up from there um is definitely
our our natural mode uh so I think that
makes it easier to to start working
together
also um it's also probably worth saying
that we have a sort of a secondary well
not secondary a very different stream of
interest in thermodynamics as well which
is the ways that we can use actual
physical thermodynamical principles to
build Hardware that is specifically has
sort of noise in it as a first class
Citizen and because of that it is
particularly well suited to
probabilistic
tasks um and so we've we've built if you
if anyone wants to look we have a Blog I
believe the url's blog. normal
computing. um and amongst other things
that are on it uh there is the very
first demonstration of using physical
thermodynamic Hardware to actually do
computations um is the computation the
most vital computation that we will ever
do it's inverting an 8 by8 Matrix so no
we can do that other ways um but it it
is sort of building up towards this idea
that we can use thermodynamics not just
in our modeling and our understanding of
the world but also in our sort of low
energy compute stack to actually realize
these things um so I think think I it's
I think it would be challenging to find
a group of people on this Earth who have
more investment in thermodynamics and
don't work in a physics
department uh because we have investment
all the way through from sort of active
influence type things all the way down
to this like this this hot thing goes
there which is kind of cool not a
physicist so I have my that's my view
that's my understanding of
thermodynamics this hot thing goes
there informative thing goes here hot
thing over there call it a day um yep
that
it's a really cool fusion with the kind
of parsimony and elegance and the
aesthetic of math and physics and first
principles and the
different parsimony of pragmatism with
the actual material basis like of a
synapse the size of the synapse and the
kind of stochasticity that that size
Alone um entails with like membranes and
all this those stochastic aspects are
leveraged for the compute the synopse is
not simply a variance
reducing machine
and
so it's like both the platonic SL
mathematical is Spirit finds a common
home in these real simple physical
demonstrations and um today it feels
like there's a big gap between the
um misos scale computational
architectures that you describe today
that are very much running on the kind
of Von noyman architecture Turing
completeness Paradigm and yet very
tantalizingly close like to a physical
object that has a
constrained
rule de facto like only one thing can
come out of this at a time as long as
the funnel is this
wide and so bring the rules and the
regularities of what we call physical
things to bear with the fundamental and
the imposed constraints on informational
spaces it's very cool
directions um one other note about just
where active inference um and action
plays a role is um and also you
mentioned like the hypotheses going
stale or like sort of data being over
relied on um in in the proactive stance
where we're using expected free energy
or something like it to to calculate
future courses of action over
observations that we haven't seen yet
moves that haven't been made yet there's
an explicit epistemic value and so that
can be diagnosed and observed as a
measure of where a given computation is
on the Continuum between purely
pragmatic value just constraint
satisficing and realizing preferences
and expectations and then the pure
epistemic value where all outcomes are
good and the more information gain the
better and then being able to take
control of that balance and know amidst
changing situations again taking
probabilistic or rule-based approach
there to when epistemic and pragmatic
like gas and break kind of come into
play these
are very basil um control knobs or
features in active inference that it's
just not going to show up at the 50th
layer of scaling is all you
need
yeah
yep cool
well do you have any other like thoughts
or things you want to add or questions
or where things are heading for your
Works nothing to add at this moment but
certainly uh excited to keep in touch
with this community and yeah
collaborating yeah absolutely um and we
sort of share I mean we write papers and
stuff but we mostly like we share most
of what we do uh be it academic in the
sort of machine learning space or be it
in the um sort of the physical Hardware
space uh on our blog which is blog.
normal
computing. um and yeah thank you so much
for inviting us it's been very fun
awesome thank you hope to speak again so
peace bye thanks
bye